<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An act and declaration of the Common Councel of the City of London, touching the late insurrection: with an order of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament, for a publique thanksgiving to be made on the next Lords-day, within the late lines of communication, for the great mercy of God in delivering the City of London from the late horrid outrage and tumult. Die Jovis, 13 April, 1648. Ordered by the Commans [sic] assembled in Parliament, that the act of the Common Councel upon the late insurrection, be printed, ... H: Elsynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</title>
            <author>City of London (England). Court of Common Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88445</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2852</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E435_22</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202790</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862967</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862967</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161590</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88445)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161590)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 68:E435[22])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An act and declaration of the Common Councel of the City of London, touching the late insurrection: with an order of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament, for a publique thanksgiving to be made on the next Lords-day, within the late lines of communication, for the great mercy of God in delivering the City of London from the late horrid outrage and tumult. Die Jovis, 13 April, 1648. Ordered by the Commans [sic] assembled in Parliament, that the act of the Common Councel upon the late insurrection, be printed, ... H: Elsynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</title>
                  <author>City of London (England). Court of Common Council.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edward Husband, Printer to the Honorable House of Commons,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>April 14. 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Riots --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161590:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN Act and Declaration OF THE <hi>COMMON CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCEL</hi> Of the City of LONDON, Touching the late INSURRECTION: WITH An ORDER of the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons aſſembled in Parliament, For a Publique Thankſgiving to be made on the next Lords-day, within the late Lines of Communication, for the great Mercy of God in delivering the City of of <hi>London</hi> from the late horrid Outrage and Tumult.</p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Die Jovis, 13 April, 1648.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ORdered by the Commans aſſembled in Parliament, That the Act of the Common Councel upon the late Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, be printed, and read on the next Lords-day, when Thanks is appointed to be given to Almighty God, the Author of this great Deliverance from the ſaid late Inſurrection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>H: Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Edward Huſband,</hi> Printer to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Houſe of <hi>Commons.</hi> April 14. 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="order_to_print">
            <pb facs="tcp:161590:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:161590:2"/>
            <head>Die Jovis, 13. April, 1648.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſolved, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THat this Houſe doth approve of the Act of the Common Councel, touching the late Inſurrection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ordered,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THat the Act of the Common Councel upon the late In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, be printed, and read on the nexts Lord Day, when thanks is appointed to be given to Almighty God, the Author of this great deliverance from the ſaid late Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H: Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <head>Die Jovis, 13. April, 1648.</head>
            <p>ORdered by the Lords and Commons in Parliament aſſembled, That a publique Thanksgiving be made by the ſeveral Miniſters within the late Lines of Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, on the next Lords Day, for the great mercy of God, in delivering the City of <hi>London</hi> from the late horrid Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Tumult; And that the Lord Major of the ſaid City do give notice thereof to the ſeveral Ministers with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſaid Lines of Communication.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H: Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:161590:3"/>
            <head>Commune Concilium tentum in Camera Guihald Civitatis London undecimo die Aprilis, <hi>1648.</hi> Anno<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> regni Domini noſtri <hi>Caroli</hi> nunc re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis Angliae, &amp;c. viceſimo quarto coram <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hanne Warner</hi> Majore civit' London, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T this Common Councel, Mr. Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Fowk</hi> and Mr. Alderman <hi>Gibs,</hi> by the directions of the Committee of the <hi>Militia</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> did make a large Relation of the great Tumult, Inſurrection and Mutiny which hapned in this City on the laſt Lords day, and on Munday laſt, by many evil diſpoſed perſons, which firſt began on the Lords-day in the afternoon in the County of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> where they ſeized the Colours of one of the Trained-Bands of the ſaid County, who were there imployed for the ſuppreſſing of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as did profane the Lords-day; and being diſperſed by ſome of the Generals Forces, did ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther together within the City of <hi>London</hi> and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties thereof, and in a Riotous maner did break open divers houſes and Magazines of Arms and Ammunition, and took away Arms, Plate, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and other things, and did ſeize upon the Drums of the Trained-Bands of this City, which were beating to raiſe their Companies, and armed themſelves, and beat up Drums, and put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:161590:3"/> in a warlike poſture, and ſeized upon the Gates, Chains and Watches of this City, and then marched to the Lord Majors houſe, and there aſſaulted the Lord Major, Sheriffs, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of the <hi>Militia</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and other Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e ſame; and did ſhoot into the Lord Majors houſe, beat back his Guards, killed one of them, wounded divers others, and ſeized and took away a piece of Ordnance from thence, with which they did afterwards ſlay and wound divers perſons, and committed many other Outrages: All which matters being largely debated, and many particulars inſiſted upon, both for the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery and Puniſhment of the ſaid Miſdemeanors and Outrages; and alſo for the preventing of the like for time to come, It was at the laſt conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and agreed by this Common Councel as followeth:</p>
            <p>Firſt, This Common Councel doth generally conceive that this City was in great danger, by reaſon of the ſaid Outrages and Miſdemeanors, and that if the ſame had not ſo timely been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented and ſtayed, the whole City would have been expoſed to the fury and rage of the ſaid Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors. And this Common Councel doth De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, That the ſame Miſdemeanor and Outrage was a horrid and deteſtable act, tending to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the City, and that they do diſavow the ſame, and with an utter deteſtation do Declare their diſlike thereof. And this Common Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel do appoint the Committee of the <hi>Militia</hi> of <hi>London</hi> to make the ſame known to the Honorable
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:161590:4"/> Houſes of Parliament, and alſo to make an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Requeſt unto them, That an Order may be iſſued forth from them to the ſeveral Miniſters of this City and the places adjacent, that they may be directed to give publique Thanks <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Almighty God, the Author of this great and wonderfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from that imminent danger wherein this City and parts adjacent were involved. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the ſaid Committee are appointed by this Court, to apply themſelves to the Honorable Houſes of Parliament, for the obtaining of a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Commiſſion of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer,</hi> for the try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and puniſhing of all the Malefactors that had a hand in this deteſtable action, according to the known Laws of this Land. And this Court with thankful hearts do acknowledge the inſtruments under God, by which they obtained this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, to be by the Forces raiſed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued by the Parliament, under the command of his Excellency the Lord General <hi>Fairfax;</hi> and to manifeſt the ſame, this Common Councel do alſo Order, That the ſaid Committee of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia,</hi> in the Name of the City, as a thing agreed upon by an unanimous conſent, ſhall return their hearty Thanks to his Excellency, for his ſpeedy and ſeaſonable Ayd afforded unto the City in this their great ſtraight and danger. And this Court with a general conſent, do well approve of the Endeavors of the ſaid Committee of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia</hi> for <hi>London,</hi> for the raiſing of the Forces of the City, and in their procuring of the ſaid ayd and help from his Excellency in this Extremity,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:161590:4"/> and what elſe they have done for the appeaſing and ſuppreſſing of the ſaid Tumults. And this Court do give Thanks to the ſaid Committee of the <hi>Militia,</hi> for their care and pains by them taken upon this ſad occaſion: And they do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point Mr. Alderman <hi>Fowk</hi> to declare the ſame their Thanks to ſuch of the ſaid Committee as are not of this Court. And this Court doth alſo with all thankfulneſs acknowledge the pains and care of the Right Honorable the Lord Major, and the Right Worſhipful the Sheriffs of this City therein. And this Court do generally De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, That it is the duty of every Citizen of this City, by himſelf and all that do belong unto him, or is under his command, to be ready upon all occaſions to be ayding and aſſiſting unto the Lord Major, and the reſt of the Magiſtrates of this City, for the ſuppreſſing of all Tumults and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders within the ſame. And the ſeveral perſons now preſent at this Common Councel, by the holding up of their hands have promiſed, That for the time to come they will uſe their utmoſt endeavor, and be ready upon all occaſions to do the ſame.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>MICHEL.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
